Guide to the Sigma Chi Fraternity collection
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Sigma Chi Fraternity collection
1933-2007
SC0754
Sigma Chi Fraternity. Alpha Omega Chapter (Stanford University).
14.75 Linear feet (27 boxes)
The collection contains financial records, including budgets, cancelled checks, receipts, invoices, pass books, investment records, bills, and accountant forms; house improvement documentation such as architectural plans and sketches, photographs, roofing samples, work orders, and safety inspection records; official documents related to insurance claims and forms, lawsuits, and ground leases signed with the Trustees of the University; Alpha Omega House Corporation records including meeting agendas, minutes, and correspondence with National organization and Stanford University; fraternity correspondence, including letters between alums, fraternity members; and publications such as chapter centennial celebration materials, STANFORD DAILY clippings, national news clippings, and copies of THE MAGAZINE OF SIGMA CHI. Additional materials not fully processed include completed surveys done at the 100th anniversary reunion, publications, correspondence, and photographs (1933-76).
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given to the Stanford University Archives by the Alpha Omega Chapter of Sigma Chi, 2005-2009, and Timothy Portwood, 2015.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Alpha Omega Chapter of Sigma Chi is one of Stanford's oldest fraternities, chartered in 1891 shortly after the opening of the University. In 1936, a collection of Sigma Chi alumni banded together to form the Alpha Omega House Corporation, a non-profit that both financed the construction of the current chapter house (finished in 1939) and continues to lease the land from the University. In 1965, the chapter was suspended from the National Sigma Chi Organization after pledging an African American student. A year later, the chapter deactivated in protest over National’s discriminatory policies and became Sigma Chi Omega, a local fraternity, which it remained for eight years. In 1974, the chapter re-affiliated with the national organization. In 1991, Sigma Chi celebrated the centennial of both the University and the chapter. In 2002, facing financial pressures, the House Corporation proposed handing the house over to the University but a new Board was installed in 2003, and proceeded to fundraise over 2.5 million dollars to refurbish the house, a project that concluded in 2006.
Chronology
1891 Sigma Chi Alpha Omega Chapter chartered at Stanford University.
1936 Alpha Omega House Corporation formed; land leased by University to AOHC to construct chapter house.
1939 Sigma Chi House completed.
1965 Sigma Chi pledges Ken Washington, an African-American student. National organization promptly suspends chapter over "violation of tradition and ritual." Chapter challenges suspension, garners national press coverage, attention of U.S. Senator (and Stanford EX alumnus) Lee Metcalf and Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.
1966 To protest discriminatory policies of National, Stanford chapter deactivates, becomes Sigma Chi Omega.
1974 Chapter re-affiliates with Sigma Chi, once again becomes Sigma Chi, Alpha Omega Chapter.
1991 Sigma Chi celebrates centennial of University and Chapter founding.
2002 House Corporation proposes hand over of house to University.
2003 Newly installed House Corporation Boards launches 2.5 million dollar "Save the House" campaign.
2006 Refurbishing of Sigma Chi House is completed.
Description of the Collection
The collection contains financial records, including budgets, cancelled checks, receipts, invoices, pass books, investment records, bills, and accountant forms; house improvement documentation such as architectural plans and sketches, photographs, roofing samples, work orders, and safety inspection records; official documents related to insurance claims and forms, lawsuits, and ground leases signed with the Trustees of the University; Alpha Omega House Corporation records including meeting agendas, minutes, and correspondence with National organization and Stanford University; fraternity correspondence, including letters between alums, fraternity members; and publications such as chapter centennial celebration materials, STANFORD DAILY clippings, national news clippings, and copies of THE MAGAZINE OF SIGMA CHI.
Materials of particular note include documentation of Sigma Chi's pledge controversy, suspension, deactivation, and eventual re-affiliation with National (boxes 11-13) and files on the proposed handover of the chapter house and subsequent fundraising drive (boxes 21-22).
Additional materials not fully processed include completed surveys done at the 100th anniversary reunion, publications, correspondence, and photographs (1933-76). Preliminary listings for these are included in this guide.
Access Terms
Sigma Chi Fraternity. Alpha Omega Chapter (Stanford University).; Greek letter societies.; Minority college students
Collection Contents
- Records, Accession ARCH-2005-129
  - Financial Records and Lease Information, 1936-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wells Fargo Bank Statements, 1948-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Wells Fargo Union Savings Pass Books, 1944-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial Reports, AOHC [Alpha Omega House Corporation], 1948-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wells Fargo Union Check Book, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and Invoices, 1951-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Loomis Sayles Mutual Fund, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wells Fargo Bank Statements, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Alpha Omega House Corporation Cancelled Checks and Financial Statements, 1938-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - University Invoices, 1947-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - EX [Sigma Chi] Financials, 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sigma Chi Bank Books, Receipts, etc, 1954-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Wells Fargo Bank Statements, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - EX paid bills, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - EX Breese Warner, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chapter Financials, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chapter Financials, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - AOHC Investments, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Active Chapter Budgets, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fiscal Statements and Budget Overviews, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Financial Advisor, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fundraising, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chapter Financial Statements, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - AOHC Finances, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - AOHC Finances, 1986-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - AOHC Finances, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - L. Tim Portwood Expenses, 1982-1990 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Checking Account, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - AO Centennial Expenses, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Financials, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Sigma Chi House and Ground Leases, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ground Leases, 1953-1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Major Repairs and Additions to Alpha Omega House, 1949-1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Policies and Premiums, 1959-1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - House Repairs and Improvements, 1960-1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ground Lease and Amendments, 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Insurance, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bathroom Renovation, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lease: Regular School Year, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - House Improvements/Engineering Reports, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Insurance, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Renovations and Improvements, 1983-1986 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - House Improvement Notes, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Summer Work Orders, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Facilities Project Manager, 1976-1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Fire Safety, 1979-1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Insurance - General, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Insurance Coverage - Donald Krebs case, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Renovations, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Coverage, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Insurance Coverage, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Work Orders and Renovations, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Earthquake Prep, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chapter Room Restoration, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Roofing Project, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Insurance, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Emergency Lighting, 1988-1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Ground Lease, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Insurance, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Chapter Rental Agreement, 1989-1992 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Repairs and Maintenance, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Summer Rent and Tax Issues, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Risk Management Foundation, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Fire Marshal Investigation and Follow up, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - House Projects/Improvements, 1993-1995 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - AOHC/National Correspondence, 1943-1947 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sigma Chi and Stanford University Fraternity System, 1958-1964 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - AOHC Minutes, 1958-1964 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Lists, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Pledge Controversy and Correspondence, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Phillip Brown's Sigma Chi National Convention Materials, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Deactivation and Correspondence, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - EX Alumni Response Letters, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Phil Brown Chapter Suspension & National Convention Documents, 1964-1966 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - House Corporation Manual, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Fraternities at Stanford Manual, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Sigma Chi Alums List and Constitution, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - DTD Beta Rho Association Manual, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Chapter Reactivation, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
  - Alumni Lists, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Lists, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - National Relations, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - University Relations/Housing, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Correspondence, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Alumni List, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - AOHC Meeting Agendas/Minutes, 1977-1981 (Box 13, Folder 67)
  - AOHC Director's Manual, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - AOHC Director's Manual, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Director's Manual, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - University Relations, 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Information From/To National, 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - AOHC and Chapter Materials and Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Golf Tournament, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Stanford/Sigma Chi Telethon, 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - AOHC Director's Manual, 1977-1986 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - AOHC Board Minutes/Agendas, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Sigma Chi Lawsuit, 1986-1988 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - University Task Force, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Stanford West Campus Region Plan, 1986-1988 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - AOHC Officers and Directors, 1981-1988 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Alcohol/Party Policy, 1984-1988 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - AOHC Agenda/Minutes and Notes, 1985-1988 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - University Relations/Clippings, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Beta, 1988-1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - AOHC Board Meeting Packets, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Rules/Guidelines, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Board Minutes/Agendas, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - National - General, 1986-1990 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - National - Drug/Alcohol Policy, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - AOHC Board Manual, 1981-1990 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Scholarships and Awards, 1988-1990 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - AOHC Accountant, 1982-1990 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - University Relations - AIFC, 1988-1991 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - University Relations - Chapter, 1989-1991 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Miscellaneous Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Agendas/Minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Centennial, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Centennial Banquet, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Centennial Handouts, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Centennial Banquet Preparations, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Banquet Responses, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Phone Effort - Centennial, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Tailgate Cancellation Phone Calls, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Sigma Chi War Dead, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Centennial - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Chapter Charter - Lucite order, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - List by Class Year, 1991 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Chapter Charter reproduction encased in Lucite (2 items) (Box 18)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - AOHC Board Minutes/Agendas, 1991-1992 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - AOHC - Pledge Orientation, 1984-1992 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Alcohol Policy, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Pledge Party Incident and Lawsuit, 1991-1993 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - AOHC Board Minutes/Agendas, 1992-1993 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Lists, 1990-1993 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - National Fraternity Relations, 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - National Relations, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Portwood Files/Greek Task Force Report, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1998 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Relations/Lists, 1996-1998 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 7-8)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2001 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2002 Jan-Apr (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2002 May-Jul (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2002 Aug-Sep (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Proposed Lease Termination, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2002 Oct (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - House Corporation Proposal, 2002 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2005 Nov-Dec (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - AOHC Portwood Files, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Save the House Campaign, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Portwood Files, 2005 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Portwood Files, 2006 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - EX Alumni Newsletter, 2006-2007 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Magazine of Sigma Chi Vols. XCIII-XCIX, 1974-1980 (Box 23)
- Additional Records, Accession ARCH-2005-301
  - Binder with materials on the history of Sigma Chi's "rebellion" over the racial discrimination issue in the 1960s and subsequent removal and reinstallation. Includes pictures and articles. (Box 1)
  - Binder with information about the old house and related subjects, miscellaneous. (Box 1)
  - Binder containing surveys filled out by attendees at the 100th anniversary reunion. Surveys include questions on why members joined and favorite Sigma Chi moments. (Box 1)
  - Articles and publications related to or referring to Sigma Chi, including information on the hoax kidnapping. (Box 1)
  - Sigma Chi stationary/envelopes. (Box 1)
  - General publications, pictures, and articles put out by Sigma Chi through their newsletter and other publications. Included are initiation tests and correspondence pertaining to rush. (Box 1)
  - Guestbook (Box 2)
  - Letters sent to alumni, flyers, and postings about upcoming events/reunions. (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence Sigma Chi-related, mostly involving Portwood. (Box 2)
- Additional Records, Accession ARCH-2007-036
  - Group photos, 1935-1936, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Photocopy of house photo, pre 1938 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, group and candid [removed from notebook and re-sleeved], 1933-1991 (Box 1)
  - Small album of photos kept by Ben Holt, class of 1935, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Sigma Chi Centennial paperweight [reproduction of old document in Lucite] (Box 1)
- Additional Records, Accession ARCH-2015-159
  - Articles of incorporation, 1935 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board Meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board Meetings, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ground lease, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stanford Alumni Newsletter: A Publication of the Alpha Omega Chapter of Sigma Chi Fraternity, 2012-2015 (Box 1, Folder 8)